Guide to The Knox Burger Archive MSS 078
Fales Library and Special Collections
Knox Burger Archive
ca. 1969-2000
Fales Library and Special Collections
Burger, Knox
MSS 078
10 Linear Feet in 10 record cartons.
Knox Burger was an editor, writer and journalist based in New York City. While serving in World War II, Burger contributed to Yank, and then after the war to such publications as Collier's. He then moved on to editing for Dell and Fawcett Publications. In 1970, he founded Knox Burger and Associates, a literary agency which later merged with the Harold Ober agency. The collection consists of Burger's correspondence from the late 1960's through 2000.
Provenance
The Knox Burger Archive was donated to the Fales Library by Knox Burger in 2000.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note:
In college, Burger was the editor of the Cornell Widow from the fall of 1942 to spring 1943. He left college in April 1943 to join the army. In the service, he contributed freelance reportage, fiction and humor to Yank, the Army Weekly. While serving with a B-29 bomb squadron in the Marianas, he covered a number of missions over Japan, and was transferred to the Yank Saipan bureau late in the summer of 1945, just before the Japanese surrender. Burger moved north to Tokyo, where he was, for a few months, the editor of the Far East edition of Yank, and wrote numerous stories about the occupation.
After the war, Burger did a brief stint at the Harvard graduate school, selling occasional fiction and articles to national magazines. In 1947, he was hired by Collier's (one of our leading defunct magazines), and became its fiction editor in 1948. In 1951, he left Collier's to edit books - mostly suspense novels - for Dell. Burger edited at Dell for 9 years, and spent 1960-1970 editing for Fawcett Publications. Among the writers he worked with during those 20 years were Kurt Vonnegut, John D. MacDonald, John Steinbeck, Ray Bradbury, Jack Finney, Horace McCoy, Walter Tevis, MacKinlay Kantor, Morris West and Louis L'Amour.
In 1970 Burger established, in partnership with his wife, Kitty Sprague, a literary agency (Knox Burger Associates), setting up in the basement of the brownstone on Washington Square in which they lived. In the spring of 2000, he merged his agency with the Harold Ober agency.
Knox Burger died in Manhattan on January 4, 2010.
Source - from a text written for Fales by Knox Burger
Scope and Content Note
The Knox Burger Archive is comprised of Burger's correspondence with and manuscripts of many notable literary figures, as well as contracts and reviews of their works. Burger's original organization of his papers was preserved as much as possible.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author.
Correspondence.; Contracts; Manuscripts for publication.; Receipts.; Clippings (information artifacts); Reviews (document genre); New York (N.Y.); Authors and publishers.; Literary agents.; Block, Lawrence; Braly, Malcolm, 1925-1980; Ashley, Steven, 1940-; Bergman, Andrew; White, Robin A.; Westlake, Donald E.; Scott, Toni; Rifkin, Shepard; Proper, Datus C.; McCaig, Donald; Mason, Robert, 1942-; Knox Burger and Associates, Ltd; Huchthausen, Peter A., 1939-; Curtis Brown, Ltd.; Caunitz, William J.; Cammarata, Phil; Byrne, Robert, 1930-; Smith, Martin Cruz, 1942-
- Series I: Manuscripts, Correspondence, Reviews, 33448
  - Early History (ca. 1969-70), 1969-1970; 31142040610118; 33581 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Abby, undated; 31142040610118; 33580 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Becker, Stephen, 1980-1995 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Bergman, Andrew: Contracts, undated; 31142040610118; 33579 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bergman, Andrew: General, undated; 31142040610118; 33578 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bergman, Andrew, undated; 31142040610118; 33577 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Block, Lawrence: Corresp. 1996-97, 1996-1997; 31142040610118; 33576 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Block, Lawrence, undated; 31142040610118; 33575 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Block, Lawrence, undated; 31142040610118; 33574 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Block, Lawrence: Story and Article Contracts and Permissions, undated; 31142040610118; 33573 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Braly, Malcolm: Contracts, undated; 31142040610118; 33572 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Braly, Malcolm: Contracts (cont'd), undated; 31142040610118; 33571 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Braly, Malcolm, undated; 31142040610118; 33570 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Braly, Malcolm, undated; 31142040610118; 33569 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Braly, Malcolm, undated; 31142040610118; 33568 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Braly, Malcolm, undated; 31142040610118; 33567 (Box 1, Folder 15, Box 9, Folder 2, Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Braly, Malcolm: Reviews and Photos, undated; 31142040610118; 33566 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bryant, Will, undated; 31142040610118; 33565 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Byrne, Robert: Corresp., undated; 31142040610118; 33564 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Byrne, Robert: Corresp., undated; 31142040610118; 33563 (Box 1, Folder 19, Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Cammarata, Phil, undated; 31142040610126; 33562 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cammarata, Phil, undated; 31142040610126; 33561 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Carse, James, undated; 31142040610126; 33560 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Caunitz, William J.: Films, undated; 31142040610126; 33559 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Caunitz, William J.: Films, undated; 31142040610126; 33558 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Caunitz, William J., undated; 31142040610126; 33557 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Caunitz, William J., undated; 31142040610126; 33556 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Caunitz, William J., undated; 31142040610126; 33555 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Conaway, James: Old Contracts, undated; 31142040610126; 33554 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Cunningham, John: Corresp., undated; 31142040610126; 33553 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Curtis Brown, Ltd., undated; 31142040610126; 33552 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Curtis Brown, Ltd., undated; 31142040610126; 33551 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Date, Shirish V., undated; 31142040610126; 33550 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Date, Shirish V., undated; 31142040610126; 33549 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Dietrich, Marlene, undated; 31142040610126; 33548 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Elliot, William, undated; 31142040610126; 33547 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Elliot, William, undated; 31142040610126; 33546 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Elliot, William, undated; 31142040610126; 33545 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Elliot, William, undated; 31142040610126; 33544 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Elliot, William, undated; 31142040610126; 33543 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Elliot, William: Reviews, undated; 31142040610126; 33542 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Finney, Jack, 1951-1989 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Fleischer, Richard, undated; 31142040610134; 33541 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Forbes, Gordon, 1960-2001 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Friday, Nancy, undated; 31142040610134; 33540 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Friedman, Meyer, undated; 31142040610134; 33539 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Gierach, John, 2000-2005 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Greenwood, L.B., undated; 31142040610134; 33538 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Huchthausen, Peter: Hostile Waters, undated; 31142040610134; 33537 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Huchthausen, Peter: Hostile Waters, undated; 31142040610134; 33536 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Johnson, Patricia, undated; 31142040610134; 33535 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Johnston, Jack, undated; 31142040610134; 33534 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Jones, Courtway, undated; 31142040610134; 33533 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Kaufman, Millard, undated; 31142040610134; 33532 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Koenig, Joe, undated; 31142040610134; 33531 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Lambert, Margaret, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - MacDonald, John D., 1966-2003 (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
  - MacDonald/Yardley, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Maclean, Norman, undated; 31142040610142; 33517 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - MacLeod, Robert, undated; 31142040610134; 33530 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - McCaig, Donald: Contracts, undated; 31142040610134; 33529 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - McCaig, Donald: Contracts (cont'd), undated; 31142040610134; 33528 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - McCaig, Donald: Ice Rider Film Corresp., undated; 31142040610134; 33527 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - McCaig, Donald: Corresp., undated; 31142040610134; 33526 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - McCaig, Donald: Corresp., undated; 31142040610134; 33525 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - McCaig, Donald: Corresp., undated; 31142040610134; 33524 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - McCaig, Donald: Corresp., undated; 31142040610134; 33523 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - McCaig, Donald: Corresp., undated; 31142040610134; 33522 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - McCaig, Donald, undated; 31142040610134; 33521 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - McCaig, Donald, undated; 31142040610134; 33520 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - McCaig, Donald, undated; 31142040610134; 33519 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - McCaig, Donald, 2000-2007 (Box 9, Folder 5-7)
  - McDermott, John, undated; 31142040610142; 33518 (Box 4, Folder 64, Box 10, Folder 2)
  - McNulty, Faith, undated; 31142040610142; 33516 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - McQuade, Walter, undated; 31142040610142; 33515 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Mason, Robert, undated; 31142040610142; 33514 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Mason, Robert, undated; 31142040610142; 33513 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Mason, Robert, undated; 31142040610142; 33512 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Mason, Robert, undated; 31142040610142; 33511 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Mason, Robert, 2004-2005 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Meredith, Scott, undated; 31142040610142; 33510 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Nurnberg, Andrew, undated; 31142040610142; 33508 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Nurnberg, Andrew, undated; 31142040610142; 33507 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Nurnberg, Andrew, undated; 31142040610142; 33506 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Nurnberg, Andrew, undated; 31142040610142; 33505 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Nurnberg, Andrew, 2000-2009 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Pearce, Donn, undated; 31142040610142; 33509 (Box 4, Folder 73, Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Pollitz, Edward A., undated; 31142040610142; 33504 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Porter, Eleanor, undated; 31142040610142; 33503 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Proper, Datus, undated; 31142040610142; 33502 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Proper, Datus, undated; 31142040610142; 33501 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Rifkin, Shepard, undated; 31142040610142; 33500 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Rifkin, Shepard, undated; 31142040610142; 33499 (Box 4, Folder 83, Box 9, Folder 10, Box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - Robson, Kenneth, undated; 31142040610142; 33498 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Rodriguez, Charles, undated; 31142040610142; 33497 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Ross, James, undated; 31142040610159; 33496 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Russell, Ross, undated; 31142040610159; 33495 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Scott, Toni, undated; 31142040610159; 33494 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Scott, Toni, undated; 31142040610159; 33493 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Seminara, George, undated; 31142040610159; 33492 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Siegel, More, undated; 31142040610159; 33491 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Smith, Douglas, undated; 31142040610159; 33490 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Tannenbaum, Robert, undated; 31142040610159; 33489 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Smith, Martin Cruz, 1970-2007 (Box 7, Folder 1-12, Box 8, Folder 4-23)
  - Tekno Books, undated; 31142040610159; 33488 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Terrall, Robert, undated; 31142040610159; 33487 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Van Atta, Winfred (Loro), undated; 31142040610159; 33486 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Victor, Ed, undated; 31142040610159; 33485 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Vistica, Gregory L., undated; 31142040610159; 33484 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Vonnegut, Mark, undated; 31142040610159; 33483 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Weisman, John, undated; 31142040610159; 33482 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610159; 33481 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610159; 33480 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610159; 33479 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610159; 33478 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610159; 33477 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610159; 33476 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Westlake, Donald: Old Contracts, undated; 31142040610159; 33475 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Westlake, Donald: Large Print, undated; 31142040610167; 33474 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Westlake, Donald: Samuel Holt, undated; 31142040610167; 33473 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610167; 33472 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610167; 33471 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610167; 33470 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Westlake, Donald, undated; 31142040610167; 33469 (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Whelton, Clark, undated; 31142040610167; 33468 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - White, Robin, undated; 31142040610167; 33467 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - White, Robin, undated; 31142040610167; 33466 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - White, Robin, undated; 31142040610167; 33465 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - White, Robin, undated; 31142040610167; 33464 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - White, Robin, undated; 31142040610167; 33463 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - White, Robin, undated; 31142040610167; 33462 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - White, Robin, undated; 31142040610167; 33461 (Box 6, Folder 121, Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Willey, Gordon, undated; 31142040610167; 33460 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Whittingham, Richard, undated; 31142040610167; 33459 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Woodley, Richard, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Wright, Leonard, undated; 31142040610167; 33458 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Yalom, Irvin D., undated; 31142040610167; 33457 (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Zeiger, Henry, undated; 31142040610167; 33456 (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - A - D, undated; 31142040610167; 33455 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - G - H, undated; 31142040610167; 33454 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - I - J - K, undated; 31142040610167; 33453 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - L - M - N, undated; 31142040610167; 33452 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - O - P - Q, undated; 31142040610167; 33451 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - T - U - V, undated; 31142040610167; 33450 (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - W - X - Y - Z, undated; 31142040610167; 33449 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Unarranged correspondence, drafts, notes, 2004-2006 (Box 9, Folder 12, Box 10, Folder 14-18, 20-28)
  - Nightcaps, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Dell-Western, Yank, undated, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, By-Laws, Bills, 1970-2006 (Box 7, Folder 13-16)
  - Carl Burger. Beaver Skins and Mountain Men., 1968 (Box 9)
  - Reporting World War II. Part Two: American Journalism 1944-1946, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Molly Knox Ostertag drawings, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 29)